I'm a brain scientist, and as a brain scientist,
أنا من علماء المخ والأعصاب، ولكوني كذلك،
I'm actually interested in how the brain learns,
فأنا مهتمة بطريقة تعلم الدماغ،
and I'm especially interested in a possibility of
وتحديدًا في إمكانية
making our brains smarter, better and faster.
جعل الدماغ أكثر ذكاءً وأفضل أداءً وسرعة.
This is in this context I'm going to tell you
وسأتحدث هنا عن ألعاب الفيديو،
about video games. When we say video games,
حينما نقول ألعاب الفيديو،
most of you think about children.
فأغلبكم يتذكر الأطفال.
It's true. Ninety percent of children do play video games.
وهذا صحيح. لأن 90% من الأطفال يلعبون ألعاب الفيديو،
But let's be frank.
لكن لنكن صريحين أكثر،
When the kids are in bed, who is in front of the PlayStation?
حينما ينام الأطفال، من يجلس أمام البلاي ستيشين؟
Most of you. The average age of a gamer is 33 years old,
أغلبكم! متوسط أعمار الذين يلعبون تبلغ أعمارهم 33 سنة
not eight years old, and in fact, if we look
لا في سن الثامنة، وفي الحقيقة
at the projected demographics of video game play,
إذا نظرنا إلى إحصائيات ألعاب الفيديو،
the video game players of tomorrow are
نجد أن لاعبي ألعاب الفيديو غدًا هم
older adults. (Laughter)
كبار السن (ضحك)
So video [gaming] is pervasive throughout our society.
إذًا فألعاب الفيديو انتشرت في مجتمعنا.
It is clearly here to stay. It has an amazing impact
ويتضح جليًا أن لها تأثيرًا كبيرًا
on our everyday life. Consider these statistics
على حياتنا اليومية، وبالنظر لهذه الإحصائيات
released by Activision. After one month of release
الصادرة عن الـأكتيفيشين بعد شهر من إصدار لعبة
of the game "Call Of Duty: Black Ops," it had been played
"Call Of Duty: Black Ops" لعبة نداء الواجب،
for 68,000 years
لُعبت على مستوى العالم على مدى 68,000 سنة
worldwide, right?
صحيح؟
Would any of you complain if this was the case
هل كان أحد منكم سيعْترض
about doing linear algebra?
إذا كان هذا هو الحال مع الجبر الخطي؟
So what we are asking in the lab is, how can we leverage that power?
فما نسأله في المعمل هو كيف يمكننا زيادة القوة؟
Now I want to step back a bit.
أريد أن أعود للوراء قليلًا.
I know most of you have had the experience of coming back
أعلم بأن أغلبكم قد خاض تجربة
home and finding your kids playing these kinds of games.
العودة للمنزل ورؤية هؤلاء الأطفال يلعبون هذه الألعاب.
(Shooting noises) The name of the game is to get
(Shooting noises) واسم اللعبة يعني
after your enemy zombie bad guys
أن تلحق بالوحوش المرعبين وهم الأشخاص السيئون
before they get to you, right?
قبل أن يصلوا إليك، صحيح؟
And I'm almost sure most of you have thought,
وأنا متأكدة بأن أغلبكم قد فكر بـ
"Oh, come on, can't you do something more intelligent
"آه، ليس لديك شيء تفعله أحسن من
than shooting at zombies?"
إطلاق النار على الزومبي؟"
I'd like you to put this kind of knee-jerk reaction
أريدكم أن تضعوا ردة فعلكم هذه
in the context of what you would have thought
في ماذا كنتم ستفعلون لو رأيتم
if you had found your girl playing sudoku
طفلتكم تلعب السودوكو
or your boy reading Shakespeare. Right?
أو ولدكم يقرأ لشكسبير؟
Most parents would find that great.
معظم الأباء سيروق لهم هذا الأمر.
Well, I'm not going to tell you that playing video games
حسنًا، أنا لن أقول بأن لعب ألعاب الفيديو
days in and days out is actually good for your health.
يوميًا مفيدٌ للصحة.
It's not, and binging is never good.
بالطبع لا، والإفراط فيه لا يعد جيدًا إطلاقًا
But I'm going to argue that in reasonable doses,
ولكني سأحاجج بأنه إذا استُخدمت استخدامًا معقولًا،
actually the very game I showed you at the beginning,
في الحقيقة اللعبة التي أريتكم إياها في البداية
those action-packed shooter games
تحديدًا ألعاب إطلاق النار المليئة بالإثارة
have quite powerful effects and positive effects
لها تأثيرات قوية وإيجابية
on many different aspects of our behavior.
في جوانب عدة من سلوكنا.
There's not one week that goes without some major
نادرًا مايمضي الأسبوع إلا ونجد العناوين الرئيسية
headlines in the media about whether video games are
في الإعلام تتحدث عمّ إن كانت ألعاب الفيديو
good or bad for you, right? You're all bombarded with that.
جيدة أو ضارة، أليس كذلك؟
I'd like to put this kind of Friday night bar discussion aside
سأجعل نقاشات شريط يوم الجمعة جانبًا
and get you to actually step into the lab.
وسنمضي للخطوة الحقيقية في المعمل.
What we do in the lab is actually measure directly,
الذي نفعله عادةً في المعمل هو القياس المباشر
in a quantitative fashion, what is the impact
بطريقة كميّة عن تأثير
of video games on the brain.
ألعاب الفيديو على الدماغ.
And so I'm going to take a few examples from our work.
وسآخذ بعض الأمثلة من عملنا.
One first saying that I'm sure you all have heard
إحدى الأقوال ومتأكدة بأنكم سمعتموه
is the fact that too much screen time
هو أن المكوث لوقت طويل أمام الشاشة
makes your eyesight worse.
تسبب ضعف البصر.
That's a statement about vision.
هذا القول عن الرؤية.
There may be vision scientists among you.
قد يكون علماء الرؤية بينكم.
We actually know how to test that statement.
نحن نعلم كيف نختبر القول.
We can step into the lab and measure how good your vision is.
نستطيع الدخول للمعامل ونقيس مدى قوة الرؤية لديك.
Well, guess what? People that don't play a lot
تخيلوا! الأشخاص الذين لا يلعبون الألعاب التفاعلية كثيرًا،
of action games, that don't actually spend a lot of time
والذين لا يقضون أوقات طويلة أمام الشاشات،
in front of screens, have normal, or what we call
تكون الرؤية لديهم طبيعية.
corrective-to-normal vision. That's okay.
أو مانسميه التصحيح إلى النظر الطبيعي، وهذا جيد.
The issue is what happens with these guys that actually
القضية هنا، ماذا يحدث لهؤلاء الأشخاص
indulge into playing video games like five hours per week,
الذين ينخرطون في لعب الألعاب الفيديو، لمدة 5 ساعات
10 hours per week, 15 hours per week.
أو 10 ساعات أو 15 ساعة أسبوعيًا.
By that statement, their vision should be really bad, right?
حسب ماقيل مسبقًا، رؤيتهم ستكون معدومة، أليس كذلك؟
Guess what? Their vision is really, really good.
تخيلوا! الرؤية لديهم جيدة جدًا
It's better than those that don't play.
بل هي أفضل حالًا من الذين لا يلعبون.
And it's better in two different ways.
أفضل من ناحيتين.
The first way is that they're actually able to resolve
الأولى، أنهم قادرين على حل التفاصيل الصغيرة
small detail in the context of clutter, and though that means
حتى مع التشويش،
being able to read the fine print on a prescription
وقادرين على قراءة ماهو مكتوب على وصفة الطبيب
rather than using magnifier glasses, you can actually do it
بدون استخدام عدسة مكبرة،
with just your eyesight.
ويمكنك القيام بذلك بالعين المجردة فقط.
The other way that they are better is actually being able
والأمر الآخر الذي يتفوقون فيه هو قدرتهم
to resolve different levels of gray.
على حل مستويات مختلفة من أسئلة الذكاء.
Imagine you're driving in a fog. That makes a difference
تخيل بأنك تسوق في الضباب، هنا يكمن الفرق
between seeing the car in front of you
بين قدرتك على رؤية السيارة التي أمامك
and avoiding the accident, or getting into an accident.
وتجنب الوقوع في الحادث، أو الوقوع فيه.
So we're actually leveraging that work to develop games
إذاً نحن نستفيد من تطوير الألعاب
for patients with low vision, and to have an impact
لمن لديهم ضعف البصر،
on retraining their brain to see better.
وللحصول على التأثير عند إعادة تدريب الدماغ ليبصروا بطريقة أفضل.
Clearly, when it comes to action video games,
ويتضح لنا أن ألعاب الفيديو التفاعلية،
screen time doesn't make your eyesight worse.
والمكوث أمام الشاشة لا يؤدي لضعف البصر.
Another saying that I'm sure you have all heard around:
هناك قول آخر وأعتقد بأنكم سمعتموه جميعًا:
Video games lead to attention problems and greater distractability.
أن ألعاب الفيديو تؤدي لمشاكلات في التركيز وتزيد التشتت
Okay, we know how to measure attention in the lab.
حسنًا، نحن نعلم كيف نقيس التركيز في المعامل
I'm actually going to give you an example of how we do so.
وسأزودكم بأمثلة توضح لكم كيف نقوم بذلك.
I'm going to ask you to participate, so you're going to have
سأطلب منكم أن تشاركوا،
to actually play the game with me. I'm going to show you
وتلعبوا معي.
colored words. I want you to shout out the color of the ink.
سأريكم كلمات ملونة، وعليكم أن تذّكروا بصوت واحد الألوان التي كتبت بها هذه الكلمات.
Right? So this is the first example.
مستعدين؟ هذا هو المثال الأول.
["Chair"]
[كرسي]
Orange, good. ["Table"] Green.
برتقالي، جيد. [طاولة] أخضر.
["Board"] Audience: Red.Daphne Bavelier: Red.
[سبورة] الجمهور: أحمر،هي: أحمر.
["Horse"] DB: Yellow. Audience: Yellow.
[حصان] هي: أصفر، الجمهور: أصفر.
["Yellow"] DB: Red. Audience: Yellow.
[حصان] هي: أحمر، الجمهور: أصفر.
["Blue"] DB: Yellow.
[أزرق] هي: أصفر.
Okay, you get my point, right? (Laughter)
حسنًا، وصل لكم مرادي، أليس كذلك؟ (ضحك)
You're getting better, but it's hard. Why is it hard?
أجدتم، ولكنها لم تكن سهلة، لماذا؟
Because I introduced a conflict between
لأن هناك تضاد بين
the word itself and its color.
الكلمات وألوان تلك الكلمات.
How good your attention is determines actually how fast
يتحدد قوة تركيزكم بمدى سرعتكم
you resolve that conflict, so the young guys here
في الإجابة،
at the top of their game probably, like, did a little better
وبطبيعة الحال الشباب
than some of us that are older.
يتفوّقون علينا نحن الأكبر منهم سنًا.
What we can show is that when you do this kind of task
مانريد إيضاحه هو أنكم حينما تقومون بهذه المهمة
with people that play a lot of action games,
مع الأشخاص الذين يلعبون الألعاب التفاعلية دائمًا،
they actually resolve the conflict faster.
فإنهم سيصلون للحل أسرع منكم،
So clearly playing those action games doesn't lead
إذًا فاللعب بهذه الألعاب التفاعلية
to attention problems.
لا تؤدي بالتأكيد إلى مشاكل في التركيز.
Actually, those action video game players have
فهؤلاء الذين يلعبون بالألعاب التفاعلية
many other advantages in terms of attention, and one
لديهم العديد من المميزات الأخرى بجانب التركيز،
aspect of attention which is also improved for the better
واحدى جوانب التركيز التي تتطور للأفضل
is our ability to track objects around in the world.
هي قدرتنا على ملاحظة الأشياء في العالم.
This is something we use all the time. When you're driving,
وهو مانستخدمه طيلة الوقت، فأنت حينما تسوق
you're tracking, keeping track of the cars around you.
فأنت تُتابع، تنتبه لسيارات التي حولك
You're also keeping track of the pedestrian, the running dog,
وتلاحظ المشاة، وترى الكلب الذي يجري
and that's how you can actually be safe driving, right?
هكذا ستكون قيادتك آمنة، أليس كذلك؟
In the lab, we get people to come to the lab,
في المعمل، نحن ندعوا الأشخاص ليحضروا إلى المعمل
sit in front of a computer screen, and we give them
وليجلسوا أمام شاشة الكمبيوتر،
little tasks that I'm going to get you to do again.
ثم نعطيهم القليل من المهام، والتي سأطلب منكم من جديد أن تطبقوها لي
You're going to see yellow happy faces
سترون وجوه صفراء سعيدة
and a few sad blue faces. These are children
ووجوه زرقاء حزينة.
in the schoolyard in Geneva during a recess
هؤلاء أطفال في فناء مدرسة في جينيف
during the winter. Most kids are happy. It's actually recess.
خلال فترة العطلة في فصل الشتاء، أغلبهم سعداء.
But a few kids are sad and blue because they've forgotten their coat.
ولكن بعضهم حزينين ويرتدون الملابس الزرقاء، لأنهم نسوا معاطفهم.
Everybody begins to move around, and your task
كلهم بدأو يتحركون، ومهمّتكم هي
is to keep track of who had a coat at the beginning
ملاحظة من كان معه المعطف في البداية
and who didn't. So I'm just going to show you an example
ومن لم يكن معه، سأريكم الآن مثالًا
where there is only one sad kid. It's easy because you can
فيه طفلٌ حزين، وسيبدو الأمرُ سهلًا
actually track it with your eyes. You can track,
لأنكم تستطيعون ملاحظة ذلك بأعينكم
you can track, and then when it stops, and there is
تستطيعون الملاحظة، وحينما يتوقف، وتظهر علامة الاستفهام،
a question mark, and I ask you, did this kid have a coat or not?
سأسألكم، هل لدى هذا الطفل جاكيت أم لا؟
Was it yellow initially or blue?
هل كانت في البداية صفراء أم زرقاء؟
I hear a few yellow. Good. So most of you have a brain. (Laughter)
سمعتُ بعضكم يقول صفراء، جيد. إذاً معظمكم يستخدمون عقولهم (ضحك)
I'm now going to ask you to do the task, but now with
لن أطلب منكم أن تقوموا بهذه المهمّة الآن،
a little more challenging task. There are going to be
لكن سأعطيكم مهمّة أصعب نوعًا ما،
three of them that are blue. Don't move your eyes.
سيكون هناك ثلاثة أطفال يرتدون اللون الأزرق، فلا تبعدوا أعينكم.
Please don't move your eyes. Keep your eyes fixated
رجاءًا لا تبعدوا أعينكم، حدّقوا النظر
and expand, pull your attention. That's the only way
وركّزوا، حتى تتمكنوا من الملاحظة.
you can actually do it. If you move your eyes, you're doomed.
تستطيعون ذلك، ولكم إذا أبعدتم أعينكم، فلن تربحوا الجولة.
Yellow or blue?
أصفر أم أزرق؟
Audience: Yellow.DB: Good.
أصفر،المتحدثة: جيد
So your typical normal young adult
إذا فلاعب الفيديو العادي البالغ
can have a span of about three or four objects of attention.
لديه القدرة على متابعة ثلاث إلى أربع كائنات
That's what we just did. Your action video game player
وهذا ماقمنا به قبل قليل، أما لاعب الألعاب التفاعلية لديه
has a span of about six to seven objects of attention,
لديه القدرة على متابعة ستة إلى سبعة كائنات
which is what is shown in this video here.
وهو مايعرضه هذا الفيديو.
That's for you guys, action video game players.
إن ألعاب الفيديو التفاعلية بالنسبة لكم
A bit more challenging, right? (Laughter)
تمثل تحديًا أليس كذلك؟ (ضحك)
Yellow or blue? Blue. We have some people
أصفر أم أزرق؟ أزرق
that are serious out there. Yeah. (Laughter)
لدينا أناسٌ جادون هناك، نعم (ضحك)
Good. So in the same way that we actually see
جيد، بنفس الطريقة التي نرى فيها
the effects of video games on people's behavior,
تأثير ألعاب الفيديو على سلوك الناس،
we can use brain imaging and look at the impact
نستطيع أن نتخيل بعقولنا تأثير
of video games on the brain, and we do find many changes,
ألعاب الفيديو على العقل، نحن نرى تغيرات كثيرة،
but the main changes are actually to the brain networks
ولكن أكبر تغير يقع على شبكات الدماغ
that control attention. So one part is the parietal cortex
الذي يتحكم بالتركيز، إذا فالجزء الأول هو الفص الجداري
which is very well known to control the orientation of attention.
والمعروف بأنه الجزء الذي يتحكم في توجّه التركيز.
The other one is the frontal lobe, which controls
والجزء الآخر هو الفص الجبهي،
how we sustain attention, and another one
وهو الذي يتحكم بكيفية محافظتنا على ثبات التركيز.
is the anterior cingulate, which controls how we allocate
والجزء الآخر وهو التلفيف الحزامي الداخلي الذي يتحكم في طريقة توزعينا للأشياء
and regulate attention and resolve conflict.
و ينظم التركيز ويحل المشكلات.
Now, when we do brain imaging, we find that all three
عندما نتخيل الآن بعقولنا، فسنرى
of these networks are actually much more efficient
أن جميع هذه الشبكات فعّالة جدًا
in people that play action games.
عند الأشخاص الذين يلعبون ألعاب الفيديو.
This actually leads me to a rather counterintuitive finding
وهذا يقودني لنتيجة حتمية
in the literature about technology and the brain.
فيما كتب عن علاقة التكنولوجيا بالدماغ.
You all know about multitasking. You all have been faulty
جميعنا يعرف عن استخدام الأجهزة المتعددة في آن واحد، ولكنكم أخطأتم في ذلك
of multitasking when you're driving
عندما تقودون السيارة
and you pick up your cellphone. Bad idea. Very bad idea.
وتتحدّثون بالجوال في آن واحد، فكرة سيئة جدًا
Why? Because as your attention shifts to your cell phone,
لمً؟ لأن تركيزك إذا تحوّل إلى هاتفك النقال،
you are actually losing the capacity to react swiftly
فأنت تفقد قدرتك على التجاوب بسرعة
to the car braking in front of you, and so you're
مع السيارة التي تتوقف أمامك،
much more likely to get engaged into a car accident.
فيصبح من المحتمل جدًا أن تصطدم بها.
Now, we can measure that kind of skills in the lab.
والآن، بإمكاننا قياس هذه المهارة في المعمل،
We obviously don't ask people to drive around and see
بطبيعة الحال نحن لن نطلب من الأشخاص أن يقودوا
how many car accidents they have. That would be a little
لكي نرى كم عدد الحوادث التي سيقعون فيها،
costly proposition. But we design tasks on the computer
لأن هذا الخيار مكلفًا، ولكننا نصمم مهام في الكمبيوتر
where we can measure, to millisecond accuracy,
تمكننا بدقّة قياسَ
how good they are at switching from one task to another.
مهارتهم في التحول من مهمة لأخرى.
When we do that, we actually find that people
وحينما نفعل ذلك، فإننا نجد أن من يلعبون ألعاب الفيديو
that play a lot of action games are really, really good.
هم أشخاص مبدعون فعلًا.
They switch really fast, very swiftly. They pay a very small cost.
يستطيعون التنقل بسهولة وسرعة، ويصرفون مبالغ قليلة جدًا.
Now I'd like you to remember that result, and put it
والآن، أريدكم أن تتذكروا تلك النتيجة،
in the context of another group of technology users,
وتنزلوها على مجموعة اخرى من مستخدمي التكنولوجيا.
a group which is actually much revered by society,
وهم المجموعة التي يوقرهم المجتمع جدًا،
which are people that engage in multimedia-tasking.
وهم من ينخرطون في استخدام العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد
What is multimedia-tasking? It's the fact that most of us,
كيف يتم استخدام العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد؟ معظمنا
most of our children, are engaged with listening to music
ومعظم أطفالنا ينسجمون مع سماع الموسيقى
at the same time as they're doing search on the web
أثناء قيامهم بالبحث على الانترنت
at the same time as they're chatting on Facebook with their friends.
وفي نفس الوقت الذي يتحدثون فيه مع أصدقائهم على الفيس بوك.
That's a multimedia-tasker.
هؤلاء هم مستخدمي العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد.
There was a first study done by colleagues at Stanford
هناك دراسة أجراها الزملاء في ستانفورد،
and that we replicated that showed that
بأننا نتكرر، وهو مايظهر ممن
those people that identify as being high multimedia-taskers
يُعرَفون بأنهم مستخدمي العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد بالدرجة الأولى
are absolutely abysmal at multitasking.
بينما هم لا يجيدون ذلك.
When we measure them in the lab, they're really bad.
فحينما نقيسهم في المعامل، نجدهم سيئون للغاية، أليس كذلك؟
Right? So these kinds of results really
فهذه النتيجة تقودنا
makes two main points.
لنقطتين أساسيتين.
The first one is that not all media are created equal.
بأن ليس كل الإعلام سواء.
You can't compare the effect of multimedia-tasking
فنحن لا نستطيع مقارنة استخدام العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد،
and the effect of playing action games. They have
بتأثير لعب الألعاب التفاعلية.
totally different effects on different aspects of cognition,
فلدى كلًا منهما تأثيرات مختلفة في جوانب مختلفة
perception and attention.
على مستوى الإدراك والإهتمام.
Even within video games, I'm telling you right now
وحتى في ألعاب الفيديو،
about these action-packed video games.
وأنا أحدثكم الآن عن ألعاب الفيديو المليئة بالإثارة،
Different video games have a different effect on your brains.
فلِألعاب الفيديو المختلفة تأثيرات مختلفة على عقولكم.
So we actually need to step into the lab and really measure
فنحتاج إذًا أن نلج المعامل
what is the effect of each video game.
لنقيس مدى تأثير ألعاب الفيديو
The other lesson is that general wisdom carries no weight.
والدرس الثاني هو أن الحكم العامة ليس لها أي معنى في الحقيقة
I showed that to you already, like we looked at the fact that
وهو ما عرضتها عليكم مسبقًا، وتوصلنا لحقيقة
despite a lot of screen time, those action gamers
أنه على الرغم من مكوث اللاعبين الطويل أمام الشاشة،
have a lot of very good vision, etc.
إلا أن لديهم العديد من الجوانب الجيدة.
Here, what was really striking is that these undergraduates
وهنا مايدهش فعلا، أن هؤلاء الطلبة الجامعيين
that actually report engaging in a lot of high
الذين ينخرطون في استخدام العديد من الأجهزة في آن واحد بالدرجة الأولى
multimedia-tasking are convinced they aced the test.
مقتنعين بأنهم أحرزوا تقادير عالية في الإختبار.
So you show them their data, you show them they are bad
فعليك أن تريهم بياناتهم وأنهم غير متفوقين،
and they're like, "Not possible." You know, they have
وأنهم كما تعلم،
this sort of gut feeling that, really, they are doing really, really good.
يشعرون بأنهم يحرزون نتائج مرضية، بل مرضية جدًا.
That's another argument for why we need to step into the lab
وهذه حجّة آخرى لسبب حاجتنا للدخول في المعامل،
and really measure the impact of technology on the brain.
ولقياس حقيقة تأثير التكنولوجيا على الدماغ.
Now in a sense, when we think about the effect
و حينما نفكر في تأثير ألعاب الفيديو على الدماغ،
of video games on the brain, it's very similar
نجد أنها بكل بساطة،
to the effect of wine on the health.
تماثل تأثير الخمر على الصحة.
There are some very poor uses of wine. There are some
هناك أضرار قليلة في شرب الخمر،
very poor uses of video games. But when consumed
وهناك أضرار قليلة في استخدام ألعاب الفيديو،
in reasonable doses, and at the right age,
لكن حينما تستهلك بجرعات معقولة، وفي عمر مناسب،
wine can be very good for health. There are actually
تكون مفيدًا للصحة.
specific molecules that have been identified
فهناك جزئيات تم تحديدها
in red wine as leading to greater life expectancy.
في الخمر الأحمر تؤدي لزيادة متوسط العمر المتوقع،
So it's the same way, like those action video games
والحال بالمثل بالنسبة لألعاب الفيديو التفاعلية،
have a number of ingredients that are actually really
إذ أنها تحتوي على عوامل
powerful for brain plasticity, learning, attention,
قوية مؤثرة على مرونة الدماغ وتعلمه وتركيزه ورؤيته وغير ذلك.
vision, etc., and so we need and we're working on
إذًا فنحن نحتاج ونعمل على محاولة استيعاب،
understanding what are those active ingredients so that
هذه المكونات النشطة حتى نستطيع
we can really then leverage them to deliver better games,
الاستفادة منها في إيصال ألعاب مناسبة،
either for education or for rehabilitation of patients.
سواءً في مجال التعليم، أو إعادة تأهيل المرضى.
Now because we are interested in having an impact
ولأننا مهتمين حاليًا أن يكون لها أثر
for education or rehabilitation of patients, we are actually
في التعليم أو في إعادة تأهيل المرضى.
not that interested in how those of you that choose
إلا أننا لسنا مهتمين بكيفية أداء هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين
to play video games for many hours on end perform.
يلعبون ألعاب الفيديو لساعات عديدة.
I'm much more interested in taking any of you
أنا مهتمة أكثر أن آخذ أيًا منكم
and showing that by forcing you to play an action game,
لأريه بأني إن أجبرته على لعب لعبة تفاعلية
I can actually change your vision for the better,
فإني أستطيع تغير رؤيته للأفضل.
whether you want to play that action game or not, right?
سواءً كنت ترغب أن تلعبها أو لا ترغب،
That's the point of rehabilitation or education.
وهذا هو هدف التعليم وإعادة التأهيل.
Most of the kids don't go to school saying,
معظم الأطفال لا يذهبون للمدرسة وهم يقولون
"Great, two hours of math!"
"جميل، لدينا حصة رياضيات لمدة ساعتين"
So that's really the crux of the research, and to do that,
وهذا هو محور موضوع البحث،
we need to go one more step.
ونحتاج لتحقيق ذلك أن نمضي خطوة للأمام،
And one more step is to do training studies.
والخطوة هي عمل دراسات معتمدة على التدريب.
So let me illustrate that step with
دعوني أوضح هذه الخطوة
a task which is called mental rotation.
بالمهمة التي تدعى بــالتدوير العقلي
Mental rotation is a task where I'm going to ask you,
والتدوير العقلي هي المهمة التي سأطلب منكم
and again you're going to do the task,
تنفيذها لي مجددًا،
to look at this shape. Study it, it's a target shape,
عليكم أن تنظروا لهذا الشكل، هذا هو الشكل المستهدف،
and I'm going to present to you four different shapes.
وسأعرض عليكم 4 أشكال مختلفة
One of these four different shapes is actually a rotated
احدى هذه االأشكال الأربعة، تمثل استدارة لهذا الشكل،
version of this shape. I want you to tell me which one:
أريدكم أن تخبروني أيًا منهم:
the first one, second one, third one or fourth one?
الأول، أم الثاني، أم الثالث، أم الرابع؟
Okay, I'll help you. Fourth one.
حسنًا سأساعدكم، الشكل الرابع
One more. Get those brains working. Come on.
حسنًا مرة آخرى، حركوا عقولكم، هيّا!
That's our target shape.
هذا هو الشكل الذي نريده.
Third. Good! This is hard, right?
الثالث، جيد! صعبة أليست كذلك؟
Like, the reason that I asked you to do that is because
السبب الذي جعلني أطلب منكم هذا الأمر
you really feel your brain cringing, right?
هو أنكم تشعرون بأن دماغكم يخذُلكم في بعض الأحيان، أليس كذلك؟
It doesn't really feel like playing mindless action video games.
لا تشابه ألعاب الفيديو القيام بالأعمال الطائشة.
Well, what we do in these training studies is, people
حسنًا، مانفعله نحن في هذه الدراسات المعتمدة على التدريب،
come to the lab, they do tasks like this one,
هو أن هناك أشخاص يذهبون للمعامل، وينجزون مهامً كهذه
we then force them to play 10 hours of action games.
ثم نجبرهم على لعب الألعاب التفاعلية مدة 10 ساعات،
They don't play 10 hours of action games in a row.
فلا يلعبون الألعاب التفاعلية مدة 10 ساعات على التوالي،
They do distributed practice, so little shots of 40 minutes
بل يقسّمون التمرينات، لحوالي 40 دقيقة مجزأة على أيام
several days over a period of two weeks.
خلال أسبوعين
Then, once they are done with the training, they come back
وبعد أن ينهوا التدريب، ويعودون بعد أيام،
a few days later and they are tested again on a similar type
يُختَبرون مجددًا في مهام مشابهة لهذا النوع،
of mental rotation task. So this is work from a colleague
هذا هو عمل الزملاء في تورنتو
in Toronto. What they showed is that, initially,
مايعرضونه هو، في البداية،
you know, subjects perform where they are expected
هل تعرفون، الأشياء تؤدي مايتوجب عليها في المكان المتوقع
to perform given their age. After two weeks of training
لترسم عهدًا لها. وبعد أسبوعين من التدرب
on action video games, they actually perform better,
على ألعاب الفيديو التفاعلية، يتحسن أدائهم
and the improvement is still there five months after
ويستمر ذلك التحسّن على مدى 5 أشهر
having done the training. That's really, really important.
بعد التدريب، وهذا مهمٌ جدًا.
Why? Because I told you we want to use these games
لمَ؟ لأني أخبرتكم بأننا نرغب في استخدام هذه الألعاب
for education or for rehabilitation. We need to have effects
لأغراضٍ تعليمية أو لإعادة التأهيل،
that are going to be long-lasting.
نحتاج لأمور لها تأثير على المدى الطويل،
Now, at this point, a number of you are probably wondering
الآن، وفي هذه النقطة تحديدًا، بعضكم يتساءل،
well, what are you waiting for, to put on the market
ماذا تنتظرون؟ أن تجدوا في السوق
a game that would be good for the attention
لعبة تشدّ انتباه جدتكم
of my grandmother and that she would actually enjoy,
وتستمتع بها حقًاـ
or a game that would be great to rehabilitate the vision
أو لعبة تعيد تأهيل رؤية حفيدكم
of my grandson who has amblyopia, for example?
الذي يعاني من الحول، مثلًا!
Well, we're working on it, but here is a challenge.
حسنًا، نحن نعمل على ذلك، ولكن هناك تحدي
There are brain scientists like me that are beginning
هناك علماء أمثالي بدأو في فهم
to understand what are the good ingredients in games
المكونات الجيدة في الألعاب
to promote positive effects, and that's what I'm going
ليعزّزوا الآثار الإيجابيّة،
to call the broccoli side of the equation.
وهذا ماسأسميه بجانب القرنبيط في التعليم.
There is an entertainment software industry
هناك صناعة للبرمجيات الترفيهة،
which is extremely deft at coming up with
والتي تستطيع فعلًا الخروج بمنتجات جذابة
appealing products that you can't resist.
لا يمكنك مقاومتها.
That's the chocolate side of the equation.
هذا هو جزء الشوكولاته في المادة التعليمية.
The issue is we need to put the two together,
القضية هي أننا نحتاج جمع الأمرين معًا،
and it's a little bit like with food.
و هو ما يشبه الطعام تقريبًا.
Who really wants to eat chocolate-covered broccoli?
من منكم يريد أكل الشوكالاتة المغلفة بالقرنبيط؟
None of you. (Laughter) And you probably have had
لا أحد (ضحك) ولابد أنكم شعرتم بذلك،
that feeling, right, picking up an education game
أليس كذلك؟
and sort of feeling, hmm, you know, it's not really fun,
اختيار لعبة تعليمية.أو مايشابهها كما تعلمون
it's not really engaging. So what we need
لا يعد ممتعًا ولن ننخرط فيه.
is really a new brand of chocolate, a brand of chocolate
إذا فكل مانحتاجه هو صنف جديدة من الشوكولاته،
that is irresistible, that you really want to play,
صنفٌ لا يقاوم، وهو ما يجعلك تريد اللعب
but that has all the ingredients, the good ingredients
ولكن لا بد أن تحتوي على جميع المكونات، والمكونات الجيدة تحديدًا
that are extracted from the broccoli that you can't recognize
التي تستخرج من القرنبيط ولا يمكنك التعرف عليها
but are still working on your brains. And we're working on it,
ومع ذلك فهي مازالت تُشغِل بالك، ونحن نعمل عليها،
but it takes brain scientists to come and to get together,
ولكنها تحتاج من علماء المخ والأعصاب أن يجتمعوا ويعملوا سويًا،
people that work in the entertainment software industry,
والأشخاص الذين يعملون في صناعة البرمجيات الترفيهيةـ
and publishers, so these are not people that usually
و الناشرين كذلك، إذا فهؤلاء ليسو هم الأشخاص الذين نلتقي بهم كل يوم
meet every day, but it's actually doable,
ولكن يمكن القيام بها،
and we are on the right track.
ونحن في المسار الصحيح.
I'd like to leave you with that thought,
سأترككم لتبحروا في هذه الفكرة،
and thank you for your attention. (Applause)
شكرًا لستماعكم (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)